<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The necessity of agreement with God: opened in a sermon preached to the Right Honourable the noble House of Peers assembled in Parliament, upon the 29th of October, 1645. being the monethly fast. / By C. Burges, D.D. preacher of the Word to the city of London. Published in obedience to an order of their Lordships.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E307_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200347</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113278</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113278)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 50:E307[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The necessity of agreement with God: opened in a sermon preached to the Right Honourable the noble House of Peers assembled in Parliament, upon the 29th of October, 1645. being the monethly fast. / By C. Burges, D.D. preacher of the Word to the city of London. Published in obedience to an order of their Lordships.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Miller for Philemon Stephens, at the signe of the golden-Lion in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Amos III, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113278:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NECESSITY OF <hi>Agreement</hi> with GOD: <hi>OPENED</hi> IN A SERMON Preached to the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Noble Houſe of PEERS aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, Vpon the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1645. being the Monethly <hi>Faſt.</hi> By C. BURGES, D. D. Preacher of the Word to the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Publiſhed in Obedience to an Order of their Lordſhips.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. Miller</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the Signe of the golden-Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113278:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113278:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE HOVSE OF PEERS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble LORDS:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE main deſigne of this plain Sermon, is, to awaken men <hi>not yet agreed with GOD,</hi> out of their golden dreams of nothing but Halcyon dayes, and mountains of perpetuall proſperity, which the almost innumerable glorious <hi>Victories</hi> heaped on your Armies, ſeem to promiſe. To effect this, I have endeavoured to put all upon the <hi>Triall</hi> of their <hi>Agreement with GOD,</hi> which being the ſoul of my Text, ought to be the chief ſubject of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. I have therein inſiſted moſt upon the <hi>examining</hi> our performance of the <hi>Nationall Covenant,</hi> which (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding your pious command, to whet the people upon it, every <hi>Faſt</hi> day) is ſo much neglected, yea deſpiſed, that he is, by ſome, ranged among the diſſolute, that now will take it; and, it is made one character of the <hi>godly party</hi> (which they who ſay, <hi>ſtand apart,</hi> appropriate,) to refuſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uniformity</hi> which we have Covenanted to promote, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſcorne. And they who (being ſenſible of the miſchiefs of no Government in the Church) preſſe the ſetling of a <hi>Diſcipline</hi> according to our Covenant, do every where hear, <hi>Rigid Presbyterians, Perſecutours, worſe than Biſhops;</hi> and what not, but what they are? None know now how to <hi>Time</hi> things, but they who while out the times to prevent the ſetling of any thing at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords,</hi> it is our happineſſe, and your honour, that you <hi>have continued with Chriſt in his temptations,</hi> and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:113278:3"/> faithfull in the midſt of a perfidious generation, when the enemy had <hi>his hour.</hi> For, what <hi>Tiberius</hi> once ſpake to <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Druſus</hi> in the Senate,<note place="margin">Tacit. <hi>Annal.</hi> lib. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ita nati eſtis, ut bona malá<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra ad Rempublicam pertineant,</hi> may be much more ſaid of you, who are ſo borne for the Publike, that you are engaged in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to promote that, what ever become of your ſelves. There is no Publike act of yours, if good, but the whole Kingdom fares the better for it; no evil that you commit, but all the Nation ſuffers by it. <hi>Be faithfull</hi> unto Chriſt (who had never more need of your Zeal) and let him alone with your ſafety and honour, untill he <hi>give you a crown of life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not enough that you act, when acted, unles you alſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en others to more expedition in that great buſines of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church. It is not ſufficient that your ſelves come up to an <hi>Agreement with God,</hi> unleſse, as <hi>Joſiah,</hi> you do your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most with all vigour, to draw others into the ſame alſo. Nor will it ſuffice that you do good your ſelves, if you wittingly ſuffer others to do evil againſt God and Chriſt, without exerciſing that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which God hath put into your hands againſt them.</p>
            <p>You remember <hi>Galba,</hi> who <q rend="inline">though innocent of much harm, which paſsed under his name, yet becauſe he permitted them to commit it, whom he ought to have bridled, or was ignorant of that which he ought to have known, loſt reputation, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a way to his own destruction.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord of Lords guide, quicken and proſper you in all the great affairs which are under your hands, make you more and more zealous for Jeſus Chriſt, that he may yet further honour you above all your Noble Progenitours, and give you hearts ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this homely piece, that it may further your Account, and not riſe up in judgement againſt you in the great day of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: in whom I am, and ever ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant, <hi>C. BURGES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113278:3"/>
            <head>THE NECESSITY OF Agreement with GOD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>AMOS 3.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Can two walke together, except they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> May begin my Sermon with the words of <hi>Cyril:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cyr. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex in loc.</note> 
               <hi>This is a deep Riddle, and a darke ſpeech.</hi> For better unfolding of it, be pleaſed to caſt your eyes on the firſt verſe of this Book, which will afford ſome light to theſe words, and to the whole Prophecie.</p>
            <p>There, you ſhall, firſt, meet a poor <hi>Herdſman</hi> of <hi>Tekoah</hi> (a City of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſix miles ſouth from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>) to wit, our <hi>Prophet,</hi> a man bred up among Cattle, and <hi>a gatherer of ſycomore-trees</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Amos 7.14, 15.</note>, ſuddenly<note n="*" place="margin">Amos rubo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum mora di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringens, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentè Propheta effectus eſt. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eron.</hi> ad <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liodor.</hi>
               </note> called of God, <hi>as he followed the flock,</hi> and ſent unto <hi>Iſrael;</hi> yea, to propheſie even at <hi>Bethel the Kings Chappel,</hi> and <hi>Court;</hi> and, there, to denounce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the King, and Kingdome, by the <hi>Aſſyrian;</hi> as, he after<note n="c" place="margin">Amos 7.9, 10, 11.</note> did.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113278:4"/>
            <p>There alſo, ſhall ye diſcover the <hi>People</hi> to, and againſt whom he propheſied; namely <hi>Iſrael:</hi> not the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but only the ten Tribes revolted from <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam.</hi> Theſe, being the major part of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> carried with them that Name. Sometimes, they are called <hi>Ephraim,</hi> from <hi>Jeroboam</hi> their firſt King, who was of that Tribe; as, that party which adhered to the Houſe of <hi>David,</hi> was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Judah,</hi> becauſe that was the Family from whence ſprang their Kings.</p>
            <p>That theſe Prophecies were directed to theſe ten Tribes, is further manifeſt by that of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> the Chief Prieſt of <hi>Bethel.</hi> Chap. 7.12, 13. <hi>O thou Seer, flee thee away into the Land of Judah, and there eat bread, and propheſie there: but propheſie not again any more at Bethel,</hi> &amp;c. which ſhews plainly, that he propheſied only to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in that place where <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the firſt had erected one of his <hi>Calves.</hi> There, <hi>Amos,</hi> for his boldneſſe againſt the Calves, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived many affronts from <hi>Amaziah</hi> the Prieſt; and, at length, a mortall blow with a Club, on his head, by <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziahs</hi> ſonne, after which he was carried home to <hi>Tekoah,</hi> where he ſoon died of that wound, as we have it from <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In vit, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</note>, and ſundry others<note n="e" place="margin">Hieron. Doroth. Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. <hi>alij<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>In that firſt verſe, thirdly, may you perceive the <hi>time</hi> when he propheſied. It was, <hi>in the dayes of Vzziah King of Judah, and in the dayes of Jeroboam the ſonne of Joaſh King of Iſrael, two years before the earthquake,</hi> a moſt remarkable cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</p>
            <p>The mention of thoſe two Kings, diſcovers <hi>Amos</hi> to have been contemporaneous with <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and <hi>Joel;</hi> yea, with <hi>Iſaiah</hi> too, (whoſe Father he was not, although ſome have ſo conjectured;) albeit he began ſomewhat after them, and finiſhed his courſe many years before them, by means of that untimely death, but now expreſſed.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113278:4"/>
            <p>Theſe Kings reigned long: <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 41 years; <hi>Vzziah,</hi> 56 years, computing from the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his age only. To the end therefore, it might be more exactly known, about what time of their ſeverall reignes <hi>Amos</hi> propheſied, it is ſaid, <hi>two years before the earthquake.</hi> This was at the time wherein <hi>Vzziah</hi> (being lifted up with his many ſucceſſes) under pretence of extraordinary devotion for many victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries obtained againſt the enemies of <hi>Judah,</hi> would needs go in perſon into the Temple and burne incenſe. The Prieſts withſtood him, as attempting that, which was lawfull for none but the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> only. He grew wroth with them: Whereupon (ſaith <hi>Ioſephus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Antiq.</hi> li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ca 11.</note>) God ſmote the place with an <hi>earthquake,</hi> and him, by a beam of the Sunne through a creviſſe of the Temple, on his mouth, which brake forth inſtantly into a lothſome leproſie: for which he was not only thruſt out of the Temple by the Prieſts, but himſelfe alſo haſted to go out, and was put from his Government to the day of his death, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p>The <hi>earthquake</hi> which then happened, ſhook all <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and was very dreadfull. For, thereby a great part of a mountain on the weſt of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in a place called <hi>Eroge,</hi> was torne off from the reſidue, and removed four furlongs out of it own place, and caſt partly into the high way, and partly into the Kings gardens, ſaith <hi>Ioſephus.</hi> This, ſo aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed and affrighted the people, that they fled from it with exceeding great fear: ſo as, this accident became extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary famous in all <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this mention is made, in <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.5. where, God threatning a ſore judgement to the enemies of Chriſt, tels them, <hi>yee ſhall flee like as yee fled from before the earthquake in the dayes of Vzziah King of Iudah.</hi> This happened in the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Vzziah,</hi> as is agreed by almoſt all Chronologers; who, with one conſent, tell us, that it fell out at the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113278:5"/> time that <hi>Vzziah</hi> was ſmitten with that lothſome Elephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiaſis.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iunius</hi> indeed diſſents: but his reaſon is eaſily anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For, albeit <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziahs</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable: yet, an <hi>earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> was more rare, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted more prodigious. Lepers were common, but <hi>earthquakes</hi> never happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but upon ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which concerned the generall.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amos</hi> began his Prophecies two years before that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digie, which muſt needs be near the end of the reign of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam</hi> the ſecond, the ſonne of <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> of the line of <hi>Iehu.</hi> For <hi>Ieroboam</hi> began his reign in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of <hi>Amaziah</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 King. 14.23.</note> father to <hi>Vzziah,</hi> who lived 14 years after <hi>Ieroboam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> ver. 2.</note>. And ſo, it muſt be about the 39<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> when the word of the Lord came firſt to <hi>Amos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This exact calculation of time is here of great uſe: for it lets us in to a clear knowledge of the ſtate and condition of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at that time when <hi>Amos</hi> uttered theſe words. It was, when <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had been often ſorely plagued with forreign, and inteſtine judgements, were now, through Gods melting compaſſions towards them, (for the Covenant with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi>) much eaſed and freed of many preſſures; their evil neighbours (who had invaded them, and encroached upon them) being van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, and diſpoſſeſſed of what they had uſurped, and all by the valour and induſtry of this <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> whom God made a great inſtrument <hi>to ſave them,</hi> as is evident, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>At this very ſeaſon (they not improving the mercy) God ſends <hi>Amos</hi> to propheſie deſtruction to the whole Kingdome; and, to utter theſe words now read unto you, by way of appeal unto themſelves to convince them of the impoſſibility of the continuance of that bleſſing, while they ſtood off with ſo much pertinacie from the Lord. For, if they ſhould (as like enough they would) plead; Can theſe things befall us? Are not we <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed? Hath not God ſtruck a Covenant with us? hath he not done many and great things for us? (Juſt as <hi>Iudah.</hi> Jer. 3.4, 5. <hi>Wilt thou not from this time cry unto me, My Father,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113278:5"/> thou art the guide of my youth, will he reſerve his anger for ever?</hi>) To which God makes anſwer, firſt, by way of <hi>conceſsion,</hi> in the verſe before my Text; It is true, <hi>You only have I known of all the families of the earth:</hi> that is, in reſpect of love, care, bounty and priviledges. Secondly, by way of <hi>Commination</hi> of the greater judgement, as a juſt cataſtrophe of their ingratitude and rebellion; <hi>Therefore will I puniſh you for all your iniquities.</hi> And, leſt they ſhould thinke this to be ſtrange ſeverity; Thirdly, He <hi>appeals</hi> to themſelves, making them the Judges in their own caſe, whether it were poſſible to be otherwiſe, ſaying; <hi>Can two walke together, except they be agreed?</hi> Which interrogation comprehends in it a more vehement denial than a bare negative could expreſſe, and muſt be reſolved into this propoſition; <hi>Two cannot poſsibly walke together, except they be agreed; Your ſelves being judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better clearing of theſe words, we muſt a little further inquire into the <hi>ſubject</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> here ſpoken of; and then into the <hi>Actions</hi> here <hi>predicated</hi> of them, and (by way of ſuppoſition) <hi>attributed</hi> to them for the more full conviction of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>ſubject</hi> is an aggregate, made up of ſeverall <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> or parties, here called <hi>Two.</hi> Who theſe <hi>Two</hi> ſhould be, Expoſitors agree not. Some underſtand it of God and the Prophet; ſome, of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſome, of God and the <hi>Aſsyrian,</hi> as <hi>agreeing</hi> to come up together to deſtroy <hi>Iſrael;</hi> others, of <hi>Salmanazer</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> agreeing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour both <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudah.</hi> But none of theſe expoſitions ſeeme ſo genuine and proper, as that which tells us that the expreſſion is Parabolicall, and therefore muſt firſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood or ſuppoſed indefinitely of any <hi>Two</hi> that can be imagined to <hi>walke together;</hi> for the Appeal lyes firſt in <hi>Theſi,</hi> whether they think it poſſible to be true of any <hi>Two</hi> in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113278:6"/> the world, not only men, but birds, beaſts, any thing. This being firſt agreed upon, they are then to conſider of what <hi>Two,</hi> in <hi>hypotheſi,</hi> he here ſpake this Parable; and, to whom, God meant they ſhould apply this Apologue, in particular. And that is, to Himſelfe, and them. For theſe two are more plainely declared before to be, <hi>I,</hi> and <hi>You. Ver.</hi> 2. that is, <hi>the Lord</hi> who ſpake againſt them, and <hi>the children of Iſrael</hi> againſt whom he ſpake <hi>Ver.</hi> 1. Theſe are the two parties, by them deſired, but by him denied, to <hi>walke together,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet <hi>agreed</hi> as they ought.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us alſo inquire into the <hi>Actions</hi> which here, by way of ſuppoſition, are <hi>attributed</hi> to theſe parties, and they are two, <hi>walking together,</hi> and <hi>agreeing together;</hi> this, being the ground of the other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Walking together,</hi> if we take it, <hi>in theſi,</hi> and in the firſt acception, imports any ſociable, familiar, friendly congreſſe or companying together, either in a journey, as thoſe two Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus, Luk.</hi> 24.17. or in ſome ſhort walke of pleaſure or delight; as, <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Achitophel, walking to the houſe of God in company. Pſal.</hi> 55.14. Hence is it tranſlated to ſignifie Gods <hi>walking</hi> with his people in a way of mercy, which is here intended, rather than <hi>walking</hi> of his people with him in a way of duty: For however it be <hi>a walking together,</hi> that here is ſpoken of, yet Gods inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereby is to declare a kinde of neceſſity of his <hi>walking contrary to them,</hi> by bringing on the <hi>Aſsyrian</hi> againſt them. And he is here giving a reaſon of it, becauſe they being not <hi>agreed</hi> with him, he could <hi>walke</hi> no longer with them in wayes of love and mercy, as he had hitherto done.</p>
            <p>Now, Gods <hi>walking</hi> with a people, contains in it theſe four particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His preſence among them, leading and protecting of them by his providence and power. This is that <hi>Preſence</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113278:6"/> of God which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo much deſired, and God promiſed, <hi>My preſence ſhall go with thee, and I will give thee reſt,</hi> Exod. 33.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His taking content and ſpeciall delight in that people with whom he vouchſafes to be in ſuch manner preſent, manifeſted by communicating unto them the very ſecrets of his heart. <hi>The Lord thy God in the midſt of thee is mighty: he will ſave, he will rejoyce over thee with joy, he will reſt in his love, he will joy over thee with ſinging.</hi> Zeph. 3.17. <hi>The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi> Pſal. 25.14. <hi>I have called you friends, for all things that I have heard of my father, I have made known unto you.</hi> Joh. 15.15.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His exceeding tenderneſſe of them, and helpfullneſſe to them in all thoſe wayes, ſtraits and difficulties wherein they walke with him. All companions in travell are ſo. (If two walke together, <hi>if they fall, the one will lift up his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</hi> Eccleſ. 4.10.) If any of the company in a journey be aſſaulted, ſicke, in any want; all contribute to his ſuccour and ſupply. It is ſo with God in walking with his people. <hi>I will walke among you, and will be your God, and ye ſhall be my people.</hi> Lev. 26.12. that is, I will do all for them that a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can do for his children. <hi>I will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. Hence that promiſe to all and every of them, <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorow the waters, I will be with thee; and thorow the rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thorow the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> Iſa. 43.2.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His being conſtant in all this goodneſſe towards them. <hi>Walking together</hi> imports, for the moſt part, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſociety, or conſtant progreſſe in the ſame way; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when applied to Morals or Spirituals. So we uſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113278:7"/> to underſtand <hi>walking with God, walking in the ſpirit, walking in the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. as is every where obvious in Scripture. So Gods <hi>walking</hi> with his people, implies a continuall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, a conſtant delight, an uninterrupted courſe of doing them good. <hi>I will never depart from them to do them good.</hi> Jer. 32.40. <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13.5.</p>
            <p>So then, Gods <hi>walking together</hi> with his people, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends in it his <hi>ſpeciall preſence</hi> with them, his <hi>delight</hi> in them, his <hi>ſupplying</hi> of them, and <hi>conſtancy</hi> of all this unto them, as being indeed their God, and making them his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For, this is a walking <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, together, <hi>per omnia,</hi> in every reſpect wherein two may be ſaid to <hi>walke together,</hi> as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> well expreſſe it. But doth he thus <hi>walke</hi> with, and towards all! No, not with any; <hi>except they be agreed.</hi> I muſt therefore now explicate what <hi>agreement</hi> is, without which there is no ſuch <hi>walking</hi> with them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Agreeing together</hi> importeth divers things; thoſe, which are more appoſite to our preſent purpoſe, are</p>
            <p n="1">1. The making of peace with an adverſary with whom we are at difference. <hi>Agree with thine adverſary quickly, whiles thou art in the way. Mat.</hi> 5.23. Between God and ſinners there is a variance, diſtance, enmity. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. This muſt be removed,<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 16.63.</note> and we reconciled. <hi>Acquaint now thy ſelfe with God, and make peace.</hi> Job 22.21. This is done when God, in Chriſt (laid hold on by faith) <hi>is pacified towards us;</hi> and we <hi>reconciled</hi> unto God by Chriſt, <hi>in the body of his fleſh through death.</hi> Col. 1.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſuitableneſſe of diſpoſition and harmony of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. This is the great attractive of amity, and motive to familiar converſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyrll.</hi> in loc.</note>. For ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nature teacheth every <hi>creature to love, and conſort it ſelfe with his like; a man, to aſſociate with ſuch as come neerest to himſelfe in qualities and conditions.</hi> Yea, our Engliſh word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113278:7"/> bears ſo much in the very forehead of it. Hence, the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers (who ſometimes make uſe of the word, turned into Latine, as a Law terme) tells us that <hi>agreeamentum,</hi> is <hi>quaſi aggregatio mentium</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr</hi> Cowel. Interpreter.</note>: Which (however a great Antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note n="l" place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hen. Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</note> and Philologiſt will not ſubſcribe unto it) is enough to aſſure us that, where there is no harmony in affections, there will be no familiarity in converſation, no <hi>walking to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:</hi> To be <hi>agreed with God</hi> then, is to come up fully to him in all ſuitableneſſe of affections, namely, to love what he loves, to hate what he hates, to rejoyce in nothing, to delight in nothing, to be grieved at nothing but what God rejoyceth, delighteth in, or grieveth at. If he love righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſo muſt they: if he hate evil, they who <hi>love the Lord</hi> muſt <hi>hate evil</hi> too. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10. <hi>Do not I hate them that hate thee?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21, 22. And this, not by hap-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, as we ſay; but, out of knowledge and choice, as knowing what diſpoſition he is of, and thereupon bringing our hearts to <hi>agreement</hi> with him. Therefore the 72. render it, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>unleſſe they know one another.</hi> This <hi>Aquila</hi> well explains by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>unleſſe they orderly accord together:</hi> which muſt import a knowledge of one anothers diſpoſition, and a due compliance therewith.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The coming up fully to a perſon with whom we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to walke, in all purpoſes, reſolutions and concluſions; that, we purpoſe not one thing, and he another; he purſue one project, we another, but the ſame: that, what counſell we take, we take of him, and conſult no other: what he would have done, and acteth in, we purſue fully with all our might. Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> fully <hi>agreed</hi> in caſting out all ſuch as ſhould <hi>confeſſe Jeſus</hi> to be <hi>Christ. Ioh.</hi> 9.22. So they who are <hi>agreed</hi> with God, purpoſe nothing, reſolve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, purſue nothing, but what he in his wiſedome purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, reſolveth and purſueth. They come <hi>fully</hi> up to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113278:8"/> minde and will of God, as <hi>Caleb, Numb.</hi> 14.24. They have no projects, hold no counſels, minde no ends, uſe no means, but what appear to be of God and for God: reſolving in this caſe, as the Apoſtle in another, (<hi>we can do nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, but for the truth,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8.) we can do nothing, project nothing, conclude nothing againſt God, but only for him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The mutuall engaging of one another by Covenant, for ever. This is the completing of all <hi>agreements,</hi> when men, to prevent diſagreements, cement themſelves by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble League. So did <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ionathan;</hi> Their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement grew up into a Covenant, that their love might receive no interruption or abatement. This was done twice<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 18.3. 1 Sam. 20.16, 17.</note> over, to make all more ſure: and the reaſon is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>becauſe</hi> each <hi>loved</hi> the other <hi>as his own ſoul.</hi> Where love makes the agreement, it will do all it can to perpetuate it. Thus God <hi>covenanteth</hi> with his people, <hi>That he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart from them to do them good,</hi> Jer. 32.40. And they (when they come up to a full <hi>agreement</hi> with him) <hi>enter into an everlasting Covenant never to be forgotten,</hi> Jer. 50.5. Yea, even wicked men perfect their <hi>agreements</hi> by a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> witneſſe thoſe, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15. who ſaid, <hi>We have made a Covenant with death, and with Hell are we at agreement:</hi> which argues a <hi>Covenant</hi> and a <hi>full agreement</hi> to be all one, who ever be the parties that ſo <hi>agree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have an explication of the words in their lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, with reference to their <hi>ſcope,</hi> to the circumſtance of <hi>time</hi> when they were ſpoken, and to the condition of the <hi>Perſons</hi> to whom they were directed. Now put all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it reſults to this maine <hi>Concluſion,</hi> which I take to be the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this Text. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Doct."/> 
               <hi>How kinde ſoever God hath been unto a people, by his preſence with them, his appearing for them, and bleſsing of them, for a long
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113278:8"/> time together; yet, there is no poſsibility that this ſhould hold alwayes, unleſſe they be perfectly reconciled unto God, and come up to a full agreement with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is, I confeſſe, a plain Point, but of ſuch great and univerſall concernment, that ſhould I ſpend the whole time allotted for this Exerciſe, in the very repeating of it over and over again, I might well avow it (as ſometimes <hi>Latimer</hi> ſaid, in a Sermon at Court, touching thoſe words, <hi>Take heed, and beware of covetouſneſſe.</hi>) to be the beſt ſpent time, that ever I had the happineſſe to imploy in ſuch an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Audience; and, the beſt ſervice that ever was perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to you, if God ſhould pleaſe to ſet it home upon your ſpirits. But becauſe ſuch I ſhould ſoon preach to the bare walls, by running ſuch a courſe. I ſhall therefore 1. Give you ſome <hi>Scriptures</hi> that declare Gods minde in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. 2. Adde ſome <hi>Inſtances</hi> of Perſons and Nations, upon whom this hath been made good. 3. Inquire into the <hi>Grounds</hi> why it muſt be ſo. 4. Shut up all with ſome <hi>Vſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For Texts of Scripture poſitively declaring this to be Gods will: one you have in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11, 12. <hi>Though a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner do evil an hundred times, and his dayes be prolonged:</hi> that is, not only ſpared, but abundantly bleſſed; (for all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are often comprehended under <hi>length of daies</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 10.12. Epheſ 6 2, 3. Prov. 3 2. &amp; ver 16. Pſal. 91.16.</note>,) <hi>yet, ſurely, I know</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe man) <hi>it ſhall be well with them that fear God, which fear before him:</hi> that is, they ſhall fare well alwayes, as being <hi>agreed</hi> with him (for, <hi>fearing of God,</hi> is put for <hi>covenanting</hi> with God; <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.40. (<hi>But it ſhall not be well with the wicked, neither ſhall he prolong his dayes which are as a ſhadow; becauſe he feareth not before him.</hi> He may proſper a while; but, a night of miſery is drawing on, that will eaſily eclypſe all his momentany happineſſe; and that, for want of <hi>agreement</hi> with God; which is the ſame with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113278:9"/> 
               <hi>not fearing of God;</hi> as from that place of <hi>Ieremy</hi> but now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, is fully manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Another Scripture you have in <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.18. <hi>The wicked worketh a deceitfull worke, but to him that ſoweth righteouſneſſe ſhall be a ſure reward.</hi> Wicked men many times pretend very fair for God; they have many ſpecious and glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to varniſh over and carry on their private intereſts and ſelfe ends. They can worke upon, and make advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of every humour, of every ſeaſon. If <hi>gain</hi> be the likelieſt lure, <hi>Demetrius</hi> knowes how to raiſe a whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in an inſtant, to baniſh <hi>Paul</hi> and his company from <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> if he but once tell them; <hi>Sirs, ye know that by this craft we have our wealth.</hi> This is argument enough to uphold the groſſeſt Idolatry in the world, among men that care for no other <hi>godlineſſe</hi> but <hi>gain, Acts</hi> 19. If Religion be in faſhion, they can, with <hi>Herod,</hi> make great ſhew of devotion, and court <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> with extraordinary reſpects, hoping that their fawning upon, and complementall complying with a man ſo eminent among the people, may make them paſſe for religious men, and carry on any deſigne under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Religion, with which the multitude (they know) are ſome times more moved, then with their own <hi>gain</hi> or <hi>liberties.</hi> But, however they may couſen uncautious men for a while, yet, <hi>mendacia non diu fallent,</hi> hypocriſie will at length be unmasked, their glozings will be in time diſcovered; and then, all that they have done will prove but a <hi>deceitfull worke</hi> to themſelves, as it was before unto others. Yea, their craft will deceive none ſo much as themſelves. Only they who are upright and ſincere with God, that <hi>ſowe righteouſneſſe,</hi> as men that are <hi>agreed</hi> with God, and are for God in uprightneſſe, reap <hi>a ſure reward,</hi> becauſe God <hi>walkes</hi> for ever with them. <hi>The end of ſuch men is peace</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113278:9"/>
            <p>As this is the Rule of Gods proceedings with parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, ſo is it the courſe which he profeſſeth to hold with whole Nations and Kingdomes. Witneſſe, <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.9, 10. where he ſaith, <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Nation and concerning a Kingdome, to build and to plant it</hi> (which is, <hi>to walke with it) if it do evil in my ſight, that it obey not my voice</hi> (which is all one with <hi>not agreeing</hi> with him) <hi>I will repent of the good wherewith I ſaid I would benefit them:</hi> that is, I will <hi>walke</hi> no longer with them. <hi>Tros Tyriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mihi nullo diſcrimine agetur.</hi> This is Gods <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>walking</hi> with Perſons and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Come we next to ſome <hi>inſtances</hi> and examples, of Perſons and Nations with whom God hath ſo proceeded.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For <hi>Perſons.</hi> Look upon <hi>Eli and his houſe, Saul,</hi> and <hi>Vzziah,</hi> as ſad examples in this kinde. As for <hi>Eli</hi> and <hi>his houſe:</hi> God had done great things for him; and ſo, had walked with him very graciouſly for a long time together. The Office of High Prieſt was ſetled upon him by ſpeciall grant of God himſelf, when in ordinary courſe it pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Eleazar</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Num. 20.26. 1 Chro 24.1, 2.</note>, (after <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> his elder bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were cut off;) <hi>Ithamar,</hi> from whom <hi>Eli</hi> ſprung, being the youngeſt<note n="p" place="margin">Num. 3.2. 1 Chro. 6.3.</note> ſonne of <hi>Aaron;</hi> And, <hi>Eli</hi> the firſt High Prieſt of <hi>Ithamars</hi> houſe, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> affirmes<note n="q" place="margin">Antiq. <hi>5.</hi> ca. ult.</note>, and <hi>Abulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>in</hi> 1 Sam. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 28.</note> proves. But when God ſaw the wickedneſſe of <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes, and his remiſſneſſe towards them, God, after all this honour, ſent him this heavy meſſage, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30, 31. <hi>I ſaid indeed, that thy houſe, and the houſe of thy father ſhould walke before me for ever: but now, the Lord ſaith, Be it farre from me. For them that honour me I will honour, and they that deſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſteemed. Behold, the dayes come that I will cut off thine arme, and the arme of thy fathers houſe,</hi> &amp;c. God firſt cut his family ſhort, and then, after four gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, took that Dignity of the High Prieſthood from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113278:10"/> his houſe. For, after <hi>Ahijah, Ahitub, Ahimelech</hi> (ſlain by <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 23.16, &amp;c.</note>,) and <hi>Abiathar</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> ver. 20.</note> (put from the Prieſthood by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that he might fullfill the word of the Lord which he ſpake concerning Elies houſe in Shiloh,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.27.) the Chief Prieſthood was taken from <hi>Ithamars</hi> line, and reſtored to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leazars</hi> family, by <hi>Solomon,</hi> who ſetled it on <hi>Zadok</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from <hi>Eleazar</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Chro. 6.8.</note>, in whoſe race it continued, not only untill the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> but even to the laſt deſtruction of the Temple and City by the <hi>Romanes.</hi> So ſevere is God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe with whom he hath ſome time <hi>walked</hi> by emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent mercies conferred on them, if care be not taken to <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with him,</hi> as he requireth, upon receit of thoſe mercies.</p>
            <p>How God <hi>walked</hi> with <hi>Saul</hi> (our next inſtance) appears in part by that of <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.17. <hi>When thou wast lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in thine own eyes, waſt thou not made Head of the Tribes of Iſrael? And the Lord anointed thee King over Iſrael:</hi> and that, when he leaſt expected it; while he was ſeeking <hi>his fathers Aſſes.</hi> But this high Honour not drawing his heart to <hi>agreement</hi> with God, <hi>the Lord rejected him from being King, ver.</hi> 26. and <hi>repented that ever he had made him King, ver.</hi> 35. He had not reigned three years when this ſentence paſſed againſt him, and began to be executed on him in a terrible manner. He held the Throne indeed 37 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that doom pronounced, (for he reigned in all 40 years<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 13.22.</note>) but liv'd and died a moſt miſerable forlorn wretch; being forſaken of God, haunted by an evil ſpirit, macerated with envy, and tearing himſelfe with rage againſt <hi>David,</hi> croſſed and curſed in every thing he went about: and, at length, when he ſaw three of his ſonnes, <hi>Jonathan, Abinadab</hi> and <hi>Malchiſhua</hi> fall in one day at <hi>Gilboa</hi> by the ſword of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> he <hi>fell upon his own ſword,</hi> and became his own butcher, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.4. His ſon <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> (the only legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate ſon that ſurvived him) did indeed by the aid of <hi>Abner,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113278:10"/> mount the Throne, and made a ſhift to keep it two years<note n="x" place="margin">2 Sam. 2.10.</note>. But, <hi>Abner</hi> (upon a baſe quarrell) revolting, two of his Captains, <hi>Baanah</hi> and <hi>Rechab,</hi> murdered him upon his bed<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 4.7.</note>, carrying his head to <hi>David</hi> to purchaſe their peace. After all this, God ſent a ſore <hi>famine</hi> upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> three years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in the reign of <hi>David, for Saul and his bloody houſe, becauſe he ſlew the Gibeonites</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.</note>, contrary to the Oath of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Joſh 9.15.</note> made to their Anceſtours: which famine could not be removed, untill <hi>David</hi> had delivered ſeven of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſonnes to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> who hung them up all in one day <hi>before the Lord in Gibeah of Saul,</hi> and ſo that plague ſtayed. Thus we ſee how <hi>contrary</hi> God walked unto <hi>Saul,</hi> both li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dead, becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> made no better uſe of Gods <hi>walking</hi> with him in advancing of him to ſo much honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vzziah</hi> (our laſt inſtance) had great experience, in the former part of his reign, of Gods <hi>walking with him</hi> in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracious manner, <hi>ſo long as Vzziah ſought the Lord in the dayes of Zechariah the Prieſt.</hi> For God made <hi>him to proſper, and helped him againſt the Philiſtines, Arabians and Mehunims,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and whom not? So that his name became great and formidable over many Countries: <hi>for he was marvellouſly helped untill he was strong,</hi> 2 Chron. 26. But then, inſtead of coming up to God fully, <hi>his heart was lifted up unto his deſtruction, for he tranſgreſſed againſt the Lord his God, and went into the Temple to burne incenſe.</hi> Then God <hi>walked contrary</hi> to him with a witneſſe. He ſmote the Temple and City with a moſt dreadfull <hi>earthquake,</hi> which ſo amazed and affrighted the whole City, that they fled out of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zech. 14.5.</note> for fear of being deſtroyed by the fall of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or opening of the earth. And, by this earthquake, a part of the roof of the Temple was opened, whereby a beam of the Sunne ſmote <hi>Vzziah</hi> on the mouth with a lothſome ſcabb, that inſtantly brake out into a terrible
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113278:11"/> Leproſie all his body over, which could never be cured to the day of his death: as was hinted before out of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From <hi>Perſons,</hi> let us aſcend to whole <hi>Nations and Kingdomes.</hi> And firſt, look upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt.</hi> How did the Lord redeem them thence, and <hi>walked with them</hi> even thorow <hi>the red ſea, going before them in a cloud by day, and in a pillar of fire by night,</hi> and <hi>bare them as a man bears his ſonne, in all the way that they went</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.31.</note>, inſomuch as within the ſpace of a very few moneths, he brought them to the very bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Canaan,</hi> even <hi>unto mount Hor, Numb.</hi> 20.23? But there, inſtead of comming up to a perfect <hi>agreement</hi> with God who had ſhewed them ſuch mercy, they fell to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring; wiſhing themſelves in <hi>Egypt</hi> again, or that they might die in the wilderneſſe, rather then adventure to go up and poſſeſſe the Land which God had promiſed them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had heard of the <hi>Anakims</hi> and other Giants there, that would oppoſe and withſtand them. For this, God inſtantly ſmote them with a very great mortality, and doomed them to a fourty years pilgrimage in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, that all who had murmured againſt him, might be cut off, before he brought their children into <hi>Canaan, Numb.</hi> 14.13. When they ſaw their errour, and ſmarted for it by the plague, they who before would not go up, when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, would now needs adventure upon it when they were forbidden; telling <hi>Moſes, Lo, we be here, and will go up to the place which the Lord hath promiſed, ver.</hi> 40. No, ſaith <hi>Moſes,</hi> it is now too late: <hi>the Lord will not go with you;</hi> and the reaſon he gives them was this, <hi>becauſe ye have turned away from the Lord, therefore the Lord will not be with you.</hi> They who would not <hi>agree with God,</hi> to go up when he bad them, found him now to <hi>walke contrary to them,</hi> when they were afterwards willing to go of their own heads: for,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113278:11"/> ſome of them who after <hi>Moſes</hi> had forbidden them, adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured <hi>preſumptuouſly up into the hill;</hi> but, <hi>the Amorites which dwelt in that mountain, came out againſt them, and chaſed them as bees, and deſtroyed them in Seir, even unto Hormah,</hi> Deut. 1.43, 44. ſelfwild obedience is but tranſgreſſion.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, when God was again pleaſed <hi>to walke</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Iſrael</hi> thorow the wilderneſſe; ſee how <hi>Moſes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth Gods tenderneſſe to him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.10, &amp;c. <hi>He found him in a deſert Land, and in the waste howling wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: He led him about, he inſtructed him, and kept him as the apple of his eye. As an Eagle stirreth up her neſt, fluttereth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her young, ſpreadeth abroad her wings, taketh them, beareth them on her wings; ſo the Lord alone did leade him,</hi> &amp;c. Here was walking with a people beyond all parallel. But when <hi>Ieſhurun waxed fat, and kicked, and forſook God which made him, and lightly eſteemed the rock of his ſalvation;</hi> God would walke no longer with him, but <hi>abhorred him, hid his face from them,</hi> and <hi>a fire was kindled in his wrath that burned to the loweſt hell,</hi> &amp;c. Thus Gods mercies abuſed turne into fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. God will not <hi>walke</hi> alwayes with <hi>Iſrael</hi> himſelfe, <hi>except</hi> He and they <hi>be agreed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſtay you with the ſtory of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after it was divided from <hi>Judah.</hi> Their Tragicall ſtory is very well known. Let us a little behold the caſe of <hi>Iudah.</hi> How much God protected, bleſſed, exalted <hi>Iudah,</hi> and delighted to walke in the midſt of her, none converſant in the ſacred ſtory can be ignorant. How farre he made <hi>Ioſiah</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall to carry on the worke of a great and glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, by purging the worſhip of God, caſheering Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and Idols, rooting out of Sodomitry, reſtoring the Paſſeover, and entring into a ſolemn Covenant, cauſing all <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſtand unto it; who is ſuch a ſtranger in <hi>Iſrael</hi> as not to know? Who would beleeve that ſuch a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113278:12"/> worke ſhould end in deſolation of the Kingdome ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; eſpecially when <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was ſo upright and ſincere, that there was no King before, or after him, like unto him?</p>
            <p>Howbeit, even then it happened to <hi>Iudah,</hi> as afterwards to the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, which by the piety and zeal of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> became Chriſtian (but not in ſincerity) yet met with ruin, inſtead of eſtabliſhment. For, notwithſtanding all this, <hi>Iudah</hi> never came up to a full <hi>agreement</hi> with God: their hearts never cloſed with him, but upon the firſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, under his ſonne <hi>Iehoahaz,</hi> revolted to Idolatry. Therefore the Lord, who had ſo highly exalted them, brought <hi>them down wonderfully</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Lam. 1.9.</note>, never leaving to <hi>walke contrary</hi> to them, untill he had <hi>romoved Iudah out of his ſight alſo,</hi> 2 King. 17.</p>
            <p>And albeit <hi>Iudah</hi> returned from <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>Jews</hi> by the <hi>Romanes</hi> was farre more bloody and fatall, then all their captivity under the <hi>Caldeans.</hi> For, in the former, we read but of 26000 captives (2 <hi>King.</hi> 24.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 52.30.) the number of the ſlain, being not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, as to be recorded. But in the other, <hi>Joſephus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Lib. <hi>7.</hi> de Bell. Iud. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> tels us that there were eleven hundred thouſand ſlain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and ninety ſeven thouſand taken priſoners; of which number eleven thouſand periſhed by famine, many were caſt to the wilde beaſts to be devoured, and others cut off by the ſword on the <hi>Romane</hi> Theatres, meerly to make them ſport at their publique ſolemnities and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. And thus ſaith the ſame Author, that famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which from the firſt foundation of it had ſtood 2177 years<note n="e" place="margin">Ibid cap ult.</note>, miſerably periſhed. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. neither her grey hayr'd antiquity, nor her infinite riches, nor her univerſall fame all the world over, nor the great glory ſhe obtained for Religion, could priviledge her from ſuch a cataſtrophe, when God, for her
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113278:12"/> not <hi>agreeing</hi> with him, ſet himſelfe to <hi>walke contrary to her.</hi> So terrible is God where great mercies have been greatly abuſed. Nor is it in vain when he ſaith of any people with whom he hath walked, <hi>Woe unto them when I depart from them,</hi> Hoſ. 9.12. It were eaſie to multiply inſtances of this kinde. The ſeven famous Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> yea, all the Eaſterne Churches who (God walking with them) were able to ſwim comfortably thorow all the bloody ſtreams of the ten Perſecutions of the Primitive Church, were at length drowned and devoured by their own errours, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, emulations, rents and ſchiſmes, and became a prey to the ſavage Saracens and Turkes unto this very day. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> yea <hi>England</hi> too can furniſh us with too many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the ſame nature, that all give teſtimony to this truth. But I forbear them, and haſten to the third thing propounded, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Grounds</hi> of the point which we have in hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Grounds</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. The <hi>Grounds</hi> of the Point.</note> and <hi>Reaſons,</hi> why this is and muſt be ſo, are manifeſt in great part from what hath been before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in opening the nature of that <hi>agreement</hi> which is here intended. I ſhall therefore touch the more briefly upon them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Enemies not reconciled, will not <hi>walke together.</hi> Yea, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> nothing is more ſhunned then the company of an enemy. One houſe, yea ſometimes one City, one Kingdome cannot hold them both. They flee one another as farre as they can. If they do meet, it is to miſchief one another, as we ſee daily in Duels and battels. If they walke together, it is as <hi>Cain</hi> walked with <hi>Abel</hi> in the field<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note>, or as <hi>Joah</hi> with <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> when <hi>Joah took him aſide in the gate to ſpeak with him peaceably,</hi> or friendly, <hi>but ſmote him on the fifth rib that he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.27.</note>: or as the ſame <hi>Joab</hi> ſaluted <hi>Amaſa,</hi> with one hand ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Amaſa</hi> by the beard to kiſſe him, and with the other
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113278:13"/> ſtabbing him to the heart<note n="g" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.9, 10.</note>. How then, can men who have not made their peace with God, nor come to any <hi>agreement with him,</hi> expect that he ſhould alwayes <hi>walke with them</hi> in a way of mercy? God and they are <hi>enemies</hi> by means of their <hi>wicked workes.</hi> And that may truly be ſaid of him and them, which himſelfe once ſpake of <hi>thoſe three ſheepherds whom he cut off in one moneth.</hi> Zech. 11.8. <hi>My ſoul loathed them, and their ſoul abhorred me.</hi> Therefore, they <hi>walke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to him,</hi> and muſt expect that he <hi>will walke contrary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Lev.</hi> 26.40, 41. Or, if he do <hi>walke with them,</hi> it will be as the executioner with a malefactour to the place of execution, as a Fowler with the birds, or as a Lion with his prey which he intends to tear and devour: <hi>When they go</hi> (ſaith the Lord of ſuch as are <hi>not agreed</hi> with him,) <hi>I will ſpread my net upon them, and bring them down as the fowls of Heaven, Hoſ.</hi> 7.12. <hi>I will be unto Ephraim as a Lion, and as a young Lion unto the houſe of Iudah: I, even I will tear, and go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, I will take away, and none ſhall reſcue them,</hi> Hoſ. 5.14. And, as one enemy takes delight in the deſtruction of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; becauſe <hi>revenge is ſweet,</hi> whatever it coſt; ſo will the Lord, in the confuſion of thoſe whom ſometimes he rejoyced over to walke with them for good. Thus himſelf expreſſely tells <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in caſe of diſobedience continued, without making their peace and <hi>agreement</hi> with him, <hi>It ſhall come to paſse, that as the Lord rejoyced over you to do you good, and to multiply you; ſo the Lord will rejoyce over you to destroy you, and to bring you to nought,</hi> Deut. 28.63.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. There can be no ſuitableneſſe of affections and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, where perſons are not <hi>agreed.</hi> What one loves the other will hate, what one deſireth the other abhorreth, what delights the one vexeth the other; If one of them be merry, the other will be ſad, or ſullen, or angry. And this muſt needs make them ſhun all <hi>walking and converſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113278:13"/> This alſo is the caſe between God and men <hi>untill they be agreed.</hi> There is no ſuitableneſſe of diſpoſition, but rather an antipathy. If God love the good, and hate the evil, men will <hi>hate the good, and love the evil, Mich.</hi> 3.2. If God <hi>delight in him that is upright in his way,</hi> Prov. 11.20. the ſame man <hi>is an abhomination to the wicked,</hi> Prov. 29.27. If they know he delights not in ſuch or ſuch a thing, they will make choice of that the rather: <hi>they chooſe that wherein I delight not,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.12. If God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in doing good, they will rejoyce in doing evil. <hi>When thou doeſt evil then thou rejoyceſt, Ier.</hi> 11.15. And upon this ground it is, that God and they <hi>cannot walke together.</hi> For therefore it is that the Lord ſeems there to ſtand and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at his peoples coming into his houſe; <hi>What hath my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved to do in my houſe?</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, what mean they to come ſo neer me that are ſo croſſe to me in diſpoſition? we can have no entercourſe together, we muſt needs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear company. There muſt be <hi>agreement in diſpoſition,</hi> before there be <hi>a walking together</hi> with any content and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They who are <hi>not agreed,</hi> do ever croſſe, and claſh in all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> their projects and deſignes; ſo as, if they do happen to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe together for a while, by reaſon of ſome common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, or publike imployments, they will yet (under-hand at leaſt) undermine and thwart one another, as <hi>Huſhai</hi> did <hi>Achitophel</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.14.</note>. So it is with men whom the Lord is pleaſed ſometimes ſo farre to walke with, as to make uſe of them in ſome ſpeciall ſervices that he ſets them upon. They may perhaps carry on his worke ſo long as Gods way and theirs lye together, but they have ever a deſigne of their own in their eye, contrary to Gods deſigne; and, they will carry on their own, whatever become of His. Therefore God uſeth them ſo farre as to bring his own counſels to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113278:14"/> paſſe by them; and in the concluſion, he falls upon them and breaks them to pieces, when he hath no further uſe of them. And ſo, he that can be content to <hi>walke with them,</hi> that is, to aſſiſt and proſper them while they be imployed in doing his worke, will walke no longer with them, when his worke is done. Thus, Gods end in ſending the <hi>Aſsyrian as the rod of his anger against an hypocriticall nation,</hi> was only to humble them for their ſins. But, the <hi>Aſsyrian meant not ſo, neither did his heart thinke ſo.</hi> He meant to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of them for himſelfe, not to ſubdue them unto God. The iſſue therefore was, that <hi>when the Lord had performed his whole worke upon mount Zion, and upon Ieruſalem, he would puniſh the fruit of the stout heart of the King of Aſsyria, and the glory of his high looks, Iſa.</hi> 10.11. So, Gods end in ſetting up <hi>Iehu,</hi> to cut off the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> was, to execute juſtice on <hi>Ahab</hi> for his Idolatries. <hi>Iehu</hi> is willing to undertake the ſervice, the reward whereof was no leſſe then a <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And, ſo farre as concerned the deſtruction of <hi>Ahab,</hi> let <hi>Iehu</hi> alone; he would not be long about it. For, no ſooner was he anointed (although but in a private room) but he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly ſet upon it<note n="i" place="margin">2 King 9.13.</note>. But, when he had cut off <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe, he ſo much minded a Crown, that, whatever <hi>his Zeal for the Lord</hi> was, he would rather be as groſſe an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later as ever <hi>Ahab</hi> was, then hazard the loſſe of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſo ſuddenly and eaſily gotten, by deſtroying thoſe Idols which <hi>Ahab</hi> worſhipped. Therefore, however God rewarded him according to his promiſe, with a lineal ſucceſſion to that Crown to the fourth generation; yet, this word being made good, the Lord would walke no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger with him, but avenged upon the houſe of <hi>Iehu</hi> that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry blood which by Gods command he ſhed in <hi>Jezreel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his hypocriſie and ſelfiſhneſſe in the doing of it. And ſo, the Lord utterly deſtroyed both him and his houſe.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113278:14"/>
            <p n="4">4. Where there is no <hi>Covenant</hi> ſtricken, there can be no <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>conſtant walking together,</hi> although there ſhould be a kinde of truce or temporary <hi>agreement</hi> for a ſeaſon. Men that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a firme and perpetuall amity and entercourſe, uſe to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle their <hi>agreement</hi> by the ſtrongeſt bond of a mutuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as <hi>Ionathan</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> Now then, when men will not come to a <hi>Covenant</hi> keeping, as well as a Covenant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with God, it is impoſſible they ſhould long <hi>agree</hi> or <hi>walke together.</hi> Their hearts will fit looſe from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and every trifling occaſion will make a breach. It is an <hi>everlaſting Covenant,</hi> that is the foundation of perpetuall friendſhip, and of walking conſtantly together in a way of love. Therefore, when God would aſſure his people that he would walke with them for ever in a way of grace and love, he ſaith, <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with them, that I will not turne away from them to do them good,</hi> Jer. 32.40. And they alſo do the like with him. <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.5. <hi>Come,</hi> ſay they, <hi>and let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> Where then there is no <hi>Covenant</hi> ſmitten, there can be no conſtant <hi>walking together;</hi> becauſe ſuch are <hi>without God in the world, Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. that is, without any ſolid intereſt in him, or league and <hi>agreement</hi> with him, that may be a foundation of conſtant mercy from him.</p>
            <p>And now (Right Honourable and Beloved) give me leave in the <hi>Vſe</hi> and application of this Point, to deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully, as for God, and from God, before whom ye are come this day to humble your ſouls, and to ſeek of him a further bleſſing upon your ſelves and all the three Kingdomes: yea, ſo to take hold of God, as to prevail with him <hi>to walke together</hi> with us in a way of bleſſing and mercy for ever.</p>
            <p>And firſt, this Point will helpe us to judge what is like to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113278:15"/> be the iſſue and event of all thoſe concuſſions and convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions under which we labour, in this time of univerſall earthquake, that, at preſent, ſeems (to the eye of ſenſe at leaſt) to threaten the demoliſhing and ſwallowing up of all the Churches of Chriſt: and how farre we may expect Gods <hi>walking</hi> with us in our troubles.</p>
            <p>It cannot, without great ingratitude and impudence, be denied that He hath graciouſly <hi>walked</hi> with our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all the time of their ſitting (even five years together, within five dayes<note n="*" place="margin">This Parlla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment began, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1640.</note>,) to the admiration, if not envy, of the neighbouring Nations. Inſomuch, as all other Proteſtant Churches and States that look Heaven-ward, have their eye and heart upon our Parliament, as <hi>Iacob</hi> upon his <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi> For, as he accounted his <hi>life</hi> to be <hi>bound up in the lads life</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 44 30.</note>, ſo they reckon their welfare and happineſſe to be wrapped up in the ſafety and proſperity of this Parliament; even as all the Popiſh crew and prophane Atheiſticall <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lialists</hi> do meaſure their hopes by the good ſucceſſe of the publique Incendiaries of this and the other two Kingdoms, in this bloody warre of theirs for the extirpation of our Religion, Laws and Liberties all at once.</p>
            <p>How hath the Lord guarded, guided and enabled our Parliament to bring back from the grave, even a dead Kingdome, whoſe Laws and Liberties had yeelded up the ghoſt; and, to revive Religion, which lay drawing on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her long home, expecting every moment to breath her laſt; Popery having long ſince prepar'd her winding-ſheet, and the ſoveraign power being imployed to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way her pillows, and to cloſe up her eyes!</p>
            <p>How marvellous have the outgoings of our God been toward our Armies even from the beginning, when it was more to bring an Army into the field, then now to lead it thorow the Kingdome! At the firſt taking up of this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113278:15"/> Warre, the Popiſh, plotting, deſtructive faction, looked upon the very Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdome who adhered to the Parliament, with as much ſuperciliouſneſſe and ſcorne, as ſometimes <hi>Tiberius</hi> and his Court-Paraſites beheld the <hi>Romane</hi> Senatours<note n="l" place="margin">O homines ad ſervitutem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti!</note>, coming in a ſervile way to viſit him, after he had, by the inſtigation of <hi>Sejanus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lewd Counſellours and companions in evil, to be rid of that great Councell withdrawn himſelfe from <hi>Rome,</hi> firſt into <hi>Campania,</hi> and then into the Iſland of <hi>Capres,</hi> where he might be moſt remote from the Senate, and more free to contrive the ruin of it, as well as to act wickedneſſe at his pleaſure with his minions, without interruption or controll. If any were ſent from our ſupreme Senate, or from the Army, with humble Petitions and ſeaſonable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, they were looked upon with ſo much contempt and ſcorne, as if they came rather to be made a ſport to all the ſcumme of man-kinde, then to offer any thing worthy the acceptance of reaſonable men. And as for the generality of this Kingdome, they having been ſo much over-awed and accuſtomed to an iron yoke of Arbitrary power, it was too too evident that the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> generoſity of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, was degenerated into ſo much poorneſſe and puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that it was a very difficult worke to draw together any conſiderable power at firſt, to withſtand that ſtrong torrent of violence and oppreſſion, which had for ſo long time carried all before it, and broke down whatever ſtood in the way to oppoſe it, and began to plead preſcription a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Law and Juſtice. Our condition therefore at that time (when the enemy preſumed that none durſt be ſo hardy as to appear in Armes againſt them) required more then ordinary ſpirits, to break the ice, and to appear in the head of an Army, or Navy, to give the firſt onſet and charge againſt a party ſo great and puiſſant, ſo inveterate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113278:16"/> and ſubtile, ſo combined, ſo many years preparing, ſo many wayes aſſiſted, and ſo ſtrongly backed and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by the Royall Majeſty, which they had alſo deeply ingaged for the deſtruction of all that the faction had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to take Armes in defence of the Royall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as well as of the Laws and Common Liberties. Yet even then God ſtirred up ſome Noble and Publike ſpirits from among <hi>the Governours of Iſrael, who offered</hi> to ſacrifice <hi>themſelves willingly among the people</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Judg. 5.9.</note>, whom God went along withall, and did great things by them, wherein we greatly rejoyced, what ever the unthankfull world (apt to cry <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> one day; and, <hi>ſtone him,</hi> the next) when their own turne is ſerved, pleaſe now to barke to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But, this laſt Summers ſucceſſes have been beyond all expectation, and almoſt beyond credibility. The right hand of the Lord hath ſo viſibly ſmitten thorow the loyns of our proud enemies, that even themſelves muſt confeſſe, God hath every where ſought for us againſt them. How many victories have been obtained! Towns and ſtrong holds wonne and recovered! and the ſtrength of the enemy how is it every where broken! This is ſo marvellous in our eyes, that we are like men that dream, ſcarce daring to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our own eyes. Oh that we could more exalt our God, and give unto him the glory due unto his Name, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo great, ſo glorious ſalvations afforded to his people by his own Almighty arme ſtretched out for them in ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a manner.</p>
            <p>But will God thus <hi>walk together</hi> with us for ever? He alone that is our ſtrength, our buckler, the horne of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and our high Tower, grant it may be ſo: and curſed be that man who ſhall ſo much as in his ſecret thoughts deſire it may be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Howbeit remember the Text, and remember the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113278:16"/> which it hath yeelded us, together with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances whereby it hath been abundantly confirmed. There muſt be an <hi>agreement</hi> (yea, another manner of <hi>ugree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> then moſt are aware of) between God and us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I dare promiſe any long continuance of his <hi>walking with us,</hi> as he hath hitherto done. Nay, I muſt pronounce the contrary from the Lord, and do here call God and all his people to witneſſe this day of that I ſpeake, namely that it is as poſſible for light to walke with darkneſſe, for Chriſt to keep company with <hi>Belial,</hi> for one contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme not to oppoſe the other, as for God and <hi>England</hi> to <hi>walke</hi> long <hi>together,</hi> while they be upon no better termes of <hi>agreement,</hi> then (for ought appears) they be yet come unto. Let our Parliament and Counſels conſult, let our Armies fight and be as proſperous and expeditious as <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> when he every where made that good, <hi>Veni, Vidi, Vici:</hi> Let the enemy be every where routed, ſcattered and ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered all to pieces before our forces; yea, let the great City be never ſo ſtrongly fortified, guarded, united, yet, unleſſe God be really and fully <hi>agreed</hi> withall, I muſt ſay <hi>(mutatis mutandis)</hi> unto them and you, as ſometimes <hi>Jeremy</hi> of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> who for a while were forced to quit their ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> when <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Army was upon their march againſt them; and when the people grew confident that now the worſt was paſt, and the danger was over; <hi>Deceive not your ſelves, ſaying, The Caldeans</hi> (I ſay, <hi>Cavaliers) ſhall ſurely depart from us: for they ſhall not depart. For though ye had ſmitten the whole Army of them that fight againſt you, and there remained but wounded men among them, yet ſhould they riſe up every man in his Tent, and burne the City with fire,</hi> Jer. 37.9, 10. It is not multitude or ſtrength will do it: <hi>there is no King</hi> (therefore no Kingdome) <hi>ſaved by the multitude of an hoſt</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 33.16.</note> They are <hi>but vain words,</hi> to ſay, <hi>I have counſell and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113278:17"/> ſtrength for the waare</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">2 King. 18.20.</note>. How ſoon can the Lord make that good upon <hi>England,</hi> which he once brought upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> Iſa. 19.11. <hi>The Princes of Zoan are fools, the counſel of the wiſe Counſellours of Pharaoh is become brutiſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let them tell thee now what the Lord of Hoſts hath purpoſed upon Egypt,</hi> ver. 12. <hi>The Princes of Zoan are become fools, the Princes of Noph are deceived, they have alſo ſeduced Egypt, even they that are the ſtay of the Tribes. The Lord hath mingled a perverſe ſpirit in the midſt thereof, and they have cauſed Egypt to erre in every worke thereof, as a drunken man ſtaggereth in his vomit,</hi> ver. 13, 14. So that we ſee it is neither ſtrength nor policy, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes nor Counſels that can ſave a people <hi>not agreed</hi> with God. To all ſuch the Lord ſaith, <hi>Woe unto them, for they have fled from mee: Destruction unto them, becauſe they have tranſgreſsed againſt mee, though I have redeemed them, yet they have ſpoken lyes againſt mee;</hi> that is, they have made falſe proteſtations and vowes unto me, of that fidelity and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which they never performed, (as ſome expound that of the Prophet) <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.13. Therefore, <hi>woe unto them.</hi> But you will perhaps plead; we are <hi>agreed</hi> with God, we have entred into ſolemne League and <hi>Covenant</hi> with him: <hi>What lack we yet?</hi> To this I anſwer, that it is not the <hi>making,</hi> but the <hi>keeping</hi> of a <hi>Covenant</hi> with all integrity and zeale, that argues our <hi>Agreement</hi> with God. For, as there be ſome, <hi>who in words profeſse to know God, yet in workes deny him;</hi> So are there not none who make a great deal of ſtirre to enter into a Covenant, and ſeem for a while to be as zealous as <hi>Joſiah,</hi> to bring all others into the ſame bond alſo; yet are <hi>Covenant-breakers,</hi> and further off from true <hi>Agreement</hi> with God, then many of the ignorant brutiſh heathens, who <hi>are ſtrangers from the Covenant of promiſe, without hope, and without God in the world</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note>. For <hi>Covenant-breakers,</hi> are ever neere of kin to <hi>haters of God, Rom.</hi> 1.30, 31. and ſo cannot
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113278:17"/> truly be, nor ſaid to be <hi>agreed with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the end therefore we may be the better and more <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> deeply humbled before the Lord this day, which is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſet apart for that purpoſe, let me adde a ſecond <hi>Vſe of Examination and Tryall,</hi> whereby we may better diſcerne whether yet we be <hi>agreed with God,</hi> or not, <hi>To ſearch and try our wayes</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 3, 40.</note>, is not only our duty, but the conſtant pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of all Gods people. Now for tryall, call to minde what hath bin ſaid in <hi>Explication</hi> of the Text, and Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Doctrine. For I love to inculcate the ſame things, rather then to abound in variety, becauſe I deſire more to profit than to pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we be <hi>agreed</hi> with God, we are <hi>reconciled</hi> to him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Reconciliation</hi> is the firſt thing in <hi>Agreement,</hi> where <hi>Enmity</hi> hath gon before. And by <hi>Reconciliation</hi> I meane, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>pacifying</hi> of Gods wrath towards us, by removing the guilt of ſinne; but the <hi>purging</hi> out of that naturall enmity and malice that is in our mindes and whole man by wicked workes, againſt the holy nature and minde of God: ſo as, there is no longer that ſtudyed and induſtrious thwarting and croſſing with him in our converſation and actions, which is dayly to be found in enemies not reconciled. Now then, is the way wardnes,<note place="margin">Trial.</note> malice and fiercenes of our natures taken off, and our hearts ſubdued unto God? Is the inward frame of our ſpirits for God, for Chriſt, for the things of God? Have we friendly and cheerfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances towards God, his wayes, and ſervants? Have we <hi>kiſſed the ſonne,</hi> as they who are content or deſirous to ſubmit to his Scepter? Or have we not rather ſent him a meſſage of defiance, by our words and actions, to let him and all the world know, <hi>we will not have this man reigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luk 19.14.</note>? If it be thus, flatter not your ſelves with vaine imaginations; Do not thinke a few good words, or the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113278:18"/> of a formall Covenant, will ſatisfy him: he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready declared your doom, <hi>Thoſe mine enemies, which would not that I ſhould reigne over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before me, Luk.</hi> 19.27.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>2</label> 2. If we be agreed with God, our ſpirits, wils and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are wholly for God, there is a ſuitablenes, corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency, ſympathy with God, we love, hate, rejoyce, greive, and exerciſe every affection as we finde God to ſtand affected. Gods joy, gains, loſſes will be accounted our own. If he be diſhonoured, reviled, reproached, we lay it to heart as falling upon our ſelves. If any wrong be done to him in his name, Ordinances, Houſe: we preſently kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle at it as done to our ſelves. <hi>For thy ſake,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>I have borne reproach, ſhame hath covered my face, the zeale of thine houſe hath eaten me up, and the reproaches of them that reproached thee, are fallen upon me, Pſal.</hi> 69.7, 9.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Trial.</note>Try then the preſent frame of our affections by this rule: Have we learned to deny not only ungodlines and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, but our own ſelves, our wit, wiſdome, deereſt affections; and to bring our hearts to an exact compliance and correſpondency with the Lord thorowout. Do we ſtudy and obſerve his diſpoſition, (as men ſtudy the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and inclinations of their Prince.) do we love, hate, rejoyce, greive, where God doth, and as God doth? Nay rather, do we not love what God hates, and hate what he loves? Do we not hate the power of Godlines, rejoyce in iniquity, repine at a thorow Reformation, greive to ſee that worke ſo likely to proſper to the prejudice of our greatnes, profits, intereſts, pleaſures, luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If this be our caſe, if we deal with God, as <hi>Peninnah</hi> with <hi>Hannah, when ſhe provoked her ſore to make her fret</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam 1.6.</note>, The Lord will be quit with us, and as we provoke him by our croſſenes and peeviſh diſpoſition, he will provoke us with a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113278:18"/> witneſſe, and reſolve, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.20. <hi>I will hide my face from them, I will ſee what their end ſhall be, for they are</hi> (a croſſe piece) <hi>a very froward generation.</hi> Their diſpoſition is very averſe from mine, there is no ſutableneſſe between me and them in <hi>affections,</hi> therefore no conſtant <hi>walking together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Where there is <hi>agreement</hi> with God, there is no dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>3</label> on of deſignes, counſels, ends of our owne that may thwart or prejudice Gods. If God require our ſervice, ayd, aſſiſtance, our anſwer will truly and readily be, like that of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> to <hi>Ahab, I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horſes as thy horſes,</hi> (1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.2.) <hi>And we will be with thee in the warre,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.3. We will not be biaſſed by correſpondences, compliances, ſelf-ends, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, any thing, but ſtudy how to promote and carry on Gods work, whatever become of our owne. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> (afterwards a <hi>Paul</hi>) before he was <hi>agreed</hi> with God, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and perſecuted Gods deſigne of ſpreading the Goſpel: but once humbled and converted, he layes aſide all his own project, and is wholly for God, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to doe? Act.</hi> 9.6. He is now no longer for perſecution of the Goſpel, which was his own buſines, but for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of it, which was Gods.<note place="margin">Trial.</note> Let us then conſider whoſe worke, ends, and intereſts we endeavour moſt to promote. Are we for God, for Chriſt, for his maine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, in all we doe? Can we be content to periſh, ſo Gods cauſe and counſells may proſper? Is it our meat and drink to doe his will, although his will ſhould thwart our own, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are we willing to adventure our ſelves and all we have for Chriſt, not counting eſtates, honours, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, no nor our very lives deare unto us, ſo we may ſet forward his Goſpel, and the power of Godlines? then take comfort. But if we make uſe of God, as cunning Polititians do one of another, pretending a great deale of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113278:19"/> reſpect and ſervice, meerly to out-wit each other, and to drive on their own ends, as <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Sejanus,</hi> of whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports, That <hi>Tiberius</hi> in favouring <hi>Sejanus</hi> had one deſigne, and <hi>Sejanus</hi> in ſerving <hi>Tiberius</hi> had another. (<hi>Tiberius</hi> meant that his affection to <hi>Sejanus</hi> ſhould be of uſe to himſelf, and <hi>Sejanus</hi> in obeying the Emperour aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Empire. <hi>Tiberius</hi> intended to ſerve him of the craft and ſubtilty of <hi>Sejanus</hi> to ruine the houſe of <hi>Germani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> and to raiſe his own: <hi>Sejanus</hi> reſolved to make his way to the Empire by the ruine of them both.) If it be with us as with God and <hi>Jehu.</hi> God meant to exalt <hi>Jehu</hi> for the ruine of <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe for Idolatry, and <hi>Jehu</hi> made uſe of Gods commiſſion and providence, to raiſe his own fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to keep up Idolatry; God will ſearch this out, and at length, as <hi>Tiberius</hi> was the ruine of his great Favourite <hi>Sejanus,</hi> ſo will God be of us, how much ſo ever he make of us at the preſent.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>4</label> 4. Where there is an <hi>Agreement</hi> with God to purpoſe, it is firmed and eſtabliſhed by a <hi>Covenant. I have ſworne, and I will perform it, that I will keep thy righteous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Pſal.</hi> 119.106. <hi>David</hi> had two things equally in his heart, the <hi>entring</hi> into a Covenant, and the <hi>keeping</hi> of it, and he bindes himſelf by an Oath unto both alike. He will not only <hi>vow,</hi> but <hi>pay.</hi> Nor will he content himſelf to doe ſo for a while, ſo long as he is in a diſtreſſe, and then (when his own turne is ſerved) ſtudy to caſt it off by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, putting new gloſſes and ſenſes upon it to elude and evade the true meaning of it, or laying aſide the vigorous execution of it (firſt, for a ſeaſon, and then altogether,) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on politique pretences. But he will keep it alwayes, <hi>even unto the end.</hi> It is with him, an <hi>everlaſting Covenant that ſhall never be forgotten</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Jer. 50.5.</note>; as well knowing that <hi>God hath no pleaſure in fooles,</hi> and that <hi>it is better not to vow,</hi> then <hi>to vow,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113278:19"/> and not pay<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.4, 5.</note> Yea, ſo punctuall was <hi>David</hi> in <hi>keeping</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, that he would never forget that which once he had made, but to a man, to <hi>Jonathan</hi> his friend: not only when he had need of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> able to ſerve him, but after <hi>Jonathan</hi> was in his grave: not only when <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe was yet ſtrong, and <hi>David</hi> but low and weak, and needed the favour and aid of the people, but after <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe was wholly reduced and broken, and <hi>David</hi> eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Kingdom, and had the remainder of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his abſolute power to ſave, or deſtroy them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.6, 7.</p>
            <p>This will try us indeed. For firſt,<note place="margin">Trial.</note> it may perhaps be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of ſome, Have ye at all taken the <hi>National Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi> Have all in power and place done their duty in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſufficient courſe that it may be adminiſtred unto all, according to the reſolution and Ordinance of Parliament in that behalf? There was great forwardnes and ſhew of extraordinary zeale in ſome to enter into that Covenant, and to preſſe it upon others, when we were low, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the aſſiſtance of our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but when we had once ingaged them, and they were come into this Kingdome, I know not how it comes to paſſe, but ſo it is, that the preſſing of the Covenant have been by degrees laid aſide, even where there was moſt need of adminiſtring it, as if it were not only ſafe, but profitable (for, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I think none do account it) to proſtitute a ſolemne ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinance of God to corrupt ends, and to be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, or caſt aſide, as the occaſions of ſtate, or the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate deſignes of ſome Projectours ſhall ſuggeſt, or require, what ever the piety and zeale of both the Honourable Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament have ordayned to the contrary. But ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>National Covenant</hi> was evil, or good. If <hi>evil,</hi> why is it not ſo declared by Authority, that we may all ſhake
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113278:20"/> it off, and be deeply and publikely humbled, for our great raſhneſſe and ſinne in entring into it. If <hi>good,</hi> why do not all take it? or, if it be not a duty, why ſhould any be bound by it, whiles others are at liberty, and act contrary to it every day? Do you think God will put up ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling with him in a matter ſo ſerious and ſacred? Be not deceived, God will not ſo be mocked: his right hand will find out all thoſe ſeeming Angels of light who thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote workes of darkneſſe, and make ſuch uſe of ſuch a ſolemne Religious act of Divine worſhip, tendred to the moſt high God, as no honeſt ingenuous Heathen durſt to make of any ſolemne piece of Idolatrous ſervice, tendred to their Idols. Will ye ſay, ſuch as theſe have <hi>agreed</hi> with God, that thus dally with God, in the moſt ſolemne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that can poſſible paſſe between God and man? There is no man ſo impudent as to affirme it, ſo ſilly as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it.</p>
            <p>But to leave them: have they who have <hi>taken</hi> the Covenant, made any conſcience to keep it? Give me leave to inſiſt upon this, for it is a principall duty of the day to conſider our breaches, and to renue our Covenant: for which end it is commanded by Authority, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Covenant ſhould be publikely read in every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, on every Faſt day. Are there not too many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, who care no more for a Covenant with God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have taken it, then <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſecond regarded his Leagues and Confederacies with any neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he would obſerve ſtrictly while the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them would advance his own ends, but deride all men as fools and idiots that thought him bound any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Are there none that have ſtrained not only their wits, but their conſciences too, to enervate and anull it, by forced gloſſes and interpretations? None that diſpute and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113278:20"/> proteſt againſt it, profeſſing they will lay down all, rather then be bound by it, and that they repent their taking of it, and declare, by their carriage to all the world, not only a thwarting of it, but a deriding of all that preſſe them with it? But I come to ſome particulars of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. I beſeech you that it may be conſidered, what <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, reality and constancie</hi> hath appeared in many, in <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion in this Kingdom,</hi> at leaſt in the matter <hi>of Diſcipline and Government according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches,</hi> thereby to <hi>bring all the three Kingdoms to the neereſt conjunction and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity therein.</hi> Be there no plottings, no bargains in the darke, to hinder that Reformation we have covenanted to promote? No ſcornes put upon that <hi>uniformity</hi> which our Covenant bindes us to endeavour? No engagements for confuſion, under the ſpecious (but falſe) name of Liberty of Conſcience, and toleration of all opinions and ſects, for fear that if the contrivers of ſuch a deſigne, ſhould pitch upon a liberty for thoſe of their own way only, they muſt needs leave ſo many out of the bargain, as would ſoon cauſe all other ſectaries to forſake them, and make them appear a very ſmall inconſiderable company, who now vapour it in all places, as if all the ſectaries in the Kingdom were for their wayes and opinions? Are there none who to effect this, caſt Remora's in the way of ſetling any thing, in hope there will be ere long a neceſſity of ſetling nothing? Be there none, who, notwithſtanding their Covenant, give it out aloud, that nothing at all, no not ſo much as the main ſubſtantials of Church-Government, ſo farre as concernes the ſtanding Officers and Ordinances of Chriſt, ought to have any ſtamp of Divine Right ſet upon it; and that there is no ſuch thing as a Church-Government in reference to Church-Cenſures to be found in Scripture, but the Civil
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113278:21"/> Magiſtrate is wholly truſted with that; and, whatever Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline be eſtabliſhed, it is to derive from the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate only? It is true, ſome things requiſite unto the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Church-Government, in reference to common order and peace, are not of Divine Inſtitution, but from the light of nature. Nor have any of thoſe who have been called to adviſe in things of this nature, affirmed otherwiſe of them. But, that therefore the very ſtanding Officers of the Church, their Offices, the Ordination of Miniſters<note n="*" place="margin">This the Parliament hath aſſerted to be <hi>the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt.</hi> See Ordinance for <hi>Ordination</hi>
               </note> and Church-Cenſures, are not inſtituted of Chriſt, no man acquainted with the Goſpel, and Kingly Office of Chriſt in any Church viſible, can with any reaſon deny.</p>
            <p>For men, then, to pretend, in a Covenant, the promoting of that Church <hi>Diſcipline and Government,</hi> which is <hi>accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches</hi> (who, as all know, do, without prejudice to the Civil Power, unanimouſly and clearly hold out the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of their Diſcipline to be of Chriſts Inſtitution:) and then to tell the Civil Magiſtrate there needs no other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment but what he pleaſeth to appoint; and that, to have no authority at all but from him, is to put him upon an action ſomewhat like that of <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch <hi>in</hi> Ph l.</note>, who commanded ſumptuous ſtatues of twelve principall gods of <hi>Greece,</hi> to be exactly made and carried before him at a great ſolemnity, with ſhew of doing much honour to the gods: but withall, he cauſed one ſtatue more to be made for himſelf, which took place of all the reſt; For which act he ſtands branded unto all poſterity, for a contemner of the gods and of all religion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What care hath been taken, <hi>without reſpect of perſons to extirpate hereſie, ſchiſme, prophaneneſſe, and what ever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſound Doctrine and the power of Godlineſse?</hi> Is there any effectuall courſe taken againſt any of theſe? Are there
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113278:21"/> not ſectaries, hereticks and hideous blaſphemers ſcattering their poiſon where ever they pleaſe, without ſuppreſſion, even after proof made of their broaching ſundry damnable opinions and blaſphemies? Is there any opinion vented, be it never ſo pernicious and deſtructive, but ſome will be found to plead for the maintainers of it, and helpe them out of the briars, when queſtioned for it? And as for <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſse,</hi> how doth it abound, and flame out in the lives of even innumerable numbers of men that have covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt it! Nor can I account them better then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, who ſuddenly leap out of the very gulf of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanneſſe, into ſome one or more of thoſe wayes and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions which they finde to be moſt in requeſt with thoſe who are able to pleaſure and preferre them; becoming great zealots in crying up (or down, as the market goes) thoſe things which they underſtand not, without giving any teſtimony of their repentance for their deboſheries and lewd converſation, or making any haſte to forſake them. Yea, is there not a way projected by ſome, to pluck up the ſluce of hell it ſelf, to let in upon us all errours and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies that ever were; and baits laid to draw the incautious heady multitude to ſwallow them all, the more to increaſe and endeer a ſtrong party to themſelves, for the better car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of private ends and intereſts?</p>
            <p n="3">3. How have we endeavoured <hi>to preſerve and maintain the Rights and Priviledges of Parliament, &amp;c.</hi> This (becauſe Magiſtracy is an Ordinance of God) is the duty of every one that fears God. For, if the Magiſtrate <hi>be the Miniſter of God to thee for thy wealth</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note>, thou art bound by the fifth Commandment, to aſſiſt and ſupport his juſt rights and authority. But, alas! are there none among us that begin to be fond of a Democracie; yea, to whiſper not only an alteration, but ſubverſion of all Government, and to bring
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113278:22"/> in Anarchy and confuſion? Is not this one of the Tenets of the Anabaptiſts which are now ſo much dandled and courted by ſome, whoſe Covenant bindes them to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their errours and fury?</p>
            <p>And of thoſe that look after this branch of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, are there none who terminate all their care and zeal, ſometimes upon one, ſometimes upon the other of the two Houſes of Parliament, as their fanſies lead them; talking of the other as if they had rather covenanted to pull it down, then to ſupport and maintain it? Are we not by the fundamentall Laws of the Kingdom (which we have fought for all this while) bound equally to preſerve the Priviledges of both Houſes? Not that any ſhould be leſſe zealous for either, but rather more. The thing I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of is, their negligence and partiality, who are not alike zealous for both. For, it cannot ſinke into any wiſe mans head, that if the one be weakned or ſleighted, the other can continue ſtrong or honourable. <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> were both the ſonnes of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and did well together, but ill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder: while they joyned, they ſcoured the ſeas of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and did what they liſt at land too, in behalf of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Therefore the <hi>Romanes</hi> erected but one Temple for both, that none might honour the one, but he muſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the other. When but one of their ſtarres appeared without the other, they who beheld it, eſpecially Mariners, were ſtricken with ſuch fear upon it, that they preſently fell to their ſuperſtitious devotions, and apprehended it as a very bad <hi>Omen,</hi> and would never give over ſacrificing, till they had obtained ſight of both together again. Let either of our <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our <hi>Tyndarides,</hi> our <hi>Gemini,</hi> our two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, begin (I will not ſay to part aſunder) but only to ſhine weakly, or to dipp in, or ſuffer an eclypſe, and farewell all our happineſſe and hopes, our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113278:22"/> Religion, ſafety, and whatever is juſtly precious and dear unto us in this world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Have there been any conſcionable obſervation of our Covenant, in the <hi>faithfull diſcovery of Incendiaries, Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnants, and evil Inſtruments that hinder Reformation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> that make <hi>diviſions</hi> among our ſelves, or between <hi>the two Kingdoms;</hi> that contrive, and raiſe <hi>factions and parties among the people, contrary to our League and Covenant?</hi> and hath there been due care uſed, to bring them to <hi>publike tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> and <hi>condigne puniſhments?</hi> Have we not rather forgotten that ever we covenanted with the great and dreadfull God, to do any ſuch thing? Are there not found among us concealers, harbourers, yea abettors of ſuch vipers? Did never any eſcape publike puniſhment, who have been, upon publike triall and conviction, condemned? Is there no where the price of blood to be found? If there be, hear what God doomed <hi>Ahab</hi> unto, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou hast let go out of thine hand, a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction, thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> This the Lord made good upon him. For how ever <hi>Benhadad</hi> crouched to <hi>Ahab</hi> at that preſent, and was content to buy his life at any rate, reſtoring all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that he or his fathers had taken from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing all peaceableneſſe and good neighbourhood to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Ahab</hi> for all time to come: Yet, at three years end, another battell is fought at <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> fatall to <hi>Ahab,</hi> who by the ſpeciall direction of the ſame <hi>Benhadad</hi> to his Captains, (<hi>to fight neither with ſmall nor great, ſave only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the King of Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 King. 22.31.</note>,) was there ſingled out and ſlain. Thus God oftentimes makes them who are unduely ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to be the deſtruction of thoſe who did not execute ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon them. Again, is there no labouring to gain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes to a <hi>party among the people?</hi> no pleading by word and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113278:23"/> writing againſt what we have bound our ſelves by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to promote? no brow-biting, blaſting and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of men of honour and approved fidelity, if they ſtand in their way? no artifices to ingage all men againſt what ever ſhall be ſetled by Parliament touching matters of Religion; as if the beſt keeping of Covenant, did conſiſt in the ſtrongeſt oppoſition againſt it? Shortly after the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Parliament, there was tampering with our Army in the North, to march Southward with a Petition; but the meaning was to force the Parliament: I hope it will not ſo ſoon be forgotten, but that the wiſedom of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Houſes will be vigilant and carefull to prevent like tamperings in all time to come.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As for the <hi>preſervation of that League and unity</hi> ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſetled between the <hi>two Kingdomes,</hi> and the <hi>bringing to puniſhment</hi> all that ſowe diviſion betwixt them; what ſhall we be able to anſwer either to God or men for the daily neglect hereof; yea, for the manifeſt endeavours of too too many to ſet them at variance, for cauſes known beſt to the contrivers of ſuch a wicked and pernicious deſigne? Albeit ſome ſpeak their fears thereof, with grief; yet, when ſuch a queſtion as this <hi>(What, ſhall we and our Brethren of Scotland fall out?)</hi> is made but the occaſion of a further diſcourſe againſt them, and to open a way to ſome confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſlander or backbiting of our Brethren in common diſcourſe, and that by thoſe who have neither certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of their actions, nor commiſſion to call them to account, thereby to worke them out of the hearts of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they can; (not ſo much to reforme things amiſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, as to be rid of them;) putting not any difference between the acts done or avowed by the Nation, or by their Commiſſioners, and thoſe faults that are made by ſome particular perſons among them; this can be no other
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113278:23"/> then a breach of our Covenant, by a cunning artifice of telling news, and a manifeſt endeavour to make a quarrell between the two Nations. And therefore (if they who have power, do not puniſh and ſuppreſſe this unſufferable liberty) God muſt needs viſit for ſuch hypocriſie, and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the quarrell of his Covenant</hi> upon all ſuch miſcreants, who will rather mingle Heaven and hell together, and break thorow all bonds that very Heathens have ever held ſacred, then miſſe of their own ends and wills, what ever become of the publike, in reſpect of Religion or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Theſe, theſe be the men that will deſtroy all, if your wiſedom and juſtice do not ſeaſonably prevent it, although the Lord ſhould give us to tread on the necks of all other enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And as <hi>for aſsiſting and defending all that enter into this Covenant in the maintaining and purſuit thereof,</hi> not ſuffering our ſelves to be by any means drawn from it, either to <hi>a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the other ſide,</hi> or to a <hi>detestable indifferency or neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality</hi> in this Cauſe of God. I report me to you, how this hath been performed. Have not many brave and gallant ſpirits received diſcouragements, been many wayes tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and at length caſt aſide as broken bottles? Nay, is there not an endeavour in ſome, ſo farre to exaſperate Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and the whole Kingdome, to break (if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) with a whole Nation that for our ſakes entred into this Covenant? Are they few that have made defection to the other ſide? and are there none who were once very hot for the Covenant, even to the puniſhing of thoſe who truly out of conſcience ſcrupled any thing in it at firſt; that are now grown cold and remiſſe; yea, are gone beyond neutrality or indifferency therein? But, to conclude this part of our Triall by the particulars of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> Let all whom this may concerne, no longer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113278:24"/> flatter themſelves with vain imaginations, that God and they be <hi>agreed:</hi> but know for certain, that there are none in the world further off from agreement with him. For he puts <hi>Covenant-breakers</hi> in the number of thoſe who are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up by him to their own luſts, and to the moſt vile and outragious abominations that can be committed by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons incurable and ordained to everlaſting deſtruction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31. So farre our fourth generall head of <hi>Trial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule. </seg>5</label> 5. Laſtly, they who are at <hi>agreement with God,</hi> agree with all his party, they heartily cloſe with his children and ſervants where ever they meet them, and are enemies to all that are enemies to God. It is ſo in all firme Leagues and Feuds. <hi>He that loves him that begat, loves him alſo that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of him,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1. And this <hi>Commandement have we from him, that he who loveth God, love his brother alſo,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.21. On the contrary, If they meet with Gods enemies, they dare make this appeal to God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21, 22. <hi>Do not I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee? and am not I grieved with thoſe that riſe up againſt thee? I hate them with perfect hatred, I count them mine enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Trial.</note>Now, conſider ſeriouſly how you ſtand affected to the faithfull ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt. Are you for them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? are they in your hearts to live and die together? do you countenance and encourage the faithfull Miniſters of Chriſt? Nay rather is not their fidelity to Chriſt, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted pride and ambition after exorbitant power? are not the godly your greateſt eye-ſores, are they not looked upon as a company of ſilly, ignorant, raſh, peeviſh men, becauſe they will not bow or bend in matters of Religion, to humane inventions of any Authority, nor depart ſo much as an hairs bredth from their principles? Or if they be ſometimes made uſe of, in caſe of neceſſity when things cannot be carried on without them, are they not afterwards
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113278:24"/> by ſome caſt aſide, as people not owned or worthy of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, eſpecially if a new generation of projectors, (men that are more malleable and fit to be moulded to ſerve turnes) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and preſent new notions &amp; projects? Or if we do make ſhew of ſome reſpect to this or that eminent man, as <hi>Herod</hi> to the Baptiſt; is it in truth of heart for the graces of God ſhining in them, or rather to grace our ſelves by counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of them? And, how ſtand we affected to all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men? are they not our chief, at leſt our ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions? Do we not ſet more by a ſcurrilous wit, a Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fone, then by an holy humble Chriſtian, whoſe ſpeech may adminiſter grace to the hearers? Who are the moſt uſuall companions of many that have given themſelves out Reformed? There is no ſurer triall of a mans inward temper of ſpirit, then by choice of his company. <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> may, in Courtſhip, comply with <hi>Ahab,</hi> but he ſhall ſurely ſmart for it; <hi>ſhouldeſt thou helpe the ungodly, and love them that hate the Lord? Therefore is wrath upon thee from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. Let them look to it, who do as he did; that while they run ſuch a courſe, they may not fooliſhly dream that God and they are <hi>agreed;</hi> for, this bred a quarrell between God and <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> although a godly Magiſtrate, and eminent for holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p>Thus have I endeavoured to bring all to the Teſt, whereupon, I doubt, it will appear that we are not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple we would be taken to be, (being yet very farre from that <hi>agreement</hi> with God which we ſtand in need of, and reſt upon, as actually made up between him and us,) nor can promiſe to our ſelves that <hi>continuance</hi> of Gods <hi>walking with us</hi> which we do expect; but have juſt cauſe to fear his ſudden departure from us, and the expoſing of us and the Kingdom to much more wo and miſery then ever we have yet felt or feared.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:113278:25"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Wherefore ſuffer the word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> unto a two-fold duty.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be deeply <hi>humbled</hi> before the Lord this day, for our want of <hi>agreement</hi> with him that hath done ſo many, ſo great things for us: for that great <hi>enmity and malignity</hi> that yet remaineth in us againſt the God of our mercies: for our <hi>croſſe affections, and peeviſh paſsions,</hi> whereby we are apt upon all occaſions to fly out againſt him; for all our <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, corrupt and baſe ends and deſignes,</hi> which thwart and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the wiſe, holy and good purpoſes and counſels of our God; for our <hi>ſtanding out and refuſing to come into the bond of his Covenant;</hi> or, <hi>dealing unfaithfully in it;</hi> for our want of <hi>Zeal for Chriſt</hi> in doing our utmoſt, <hi>in our ſeverall places and callings,</hi> to promote <hi>the Reformation of Religion in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> not only in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> but in <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> according to our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; for our great lukewarmneſſe in not endeavouring, as we ought, to <hi>extirpate ſuperſtition, hereſie, ſchiſme, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe and what ever is contrary to ſound Doctrine and the power of godlineſse,</hi> whereby we do in great part <hi>partake of other mens ſinnes,</hi> and bring our ſelves into apparent danger to <hi>receive of their plagues;</hi> for want of that <hi>reality,</hi> impartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and <hi>conſtancy in preſerving the Priviledges of Parliament, and liberties of the Kingdome,</hi> which we ought upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions to expreſſe; many growing weary of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and clamouring againſt it as one of our greateſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and abuſing the Liberties of the Kingdome to all licentiouſneſſe and confuſion: for want of courage and <hi>faithfullneſse</hi> in the <hi>diſcovery of all Incendiaries, Malignants and evil inſtruments,</hi> that do palpably and openly <hi>hinder</hi> and oppoſe that <hi>Reformation of Religion</hi> which we have bound our ſelves by Covenant to promote; or that ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undermine and way-lay all endeavours of Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113278:25"/> 
               <hi>the King and his people,</hi> or, that labour to make <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> between the <hi>two Kingdoms,</hi> or <hi>factions and parties among the people, contrary to our Nationall League and Covenant:</hi> for want of zeal in doing all we can, <hi>according to our places and interests,</hi> to maintain and preſerve that <hi>bleſsed Peace</hi> ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſetled between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they might <hi>remain conjoyned in a firme League and union to all poſterity, and that juſtice may be done upon the wilfull oppoſers thereof:</hi> for our great unwillingneſſe conſtantly <hi>to aſsiſt and defend all thoſe that, in this common Cauſe of Religion, Liberty and Peace of the Kingdomes, enter into the Nationall League and Covenant:</hi> for our aptneſſe to be <hi>withdrawn from that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Vnion and Conjunction,</hi> to the <hi>other ſide,</hi> or at leſt to <hi>a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable indifferency or neutrality</hi> in the Publike <hi>Cauſe, which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms, and the honour of the King:</hi> for our not <hi>humbling</hi> our ſelves even unto this day: <hi>for our own ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of all the three Kingdomes:</hi> for <hi>undervaluing the Goſpel:</hi> for <hi>not receiving Chriſt into our hearts, and walking worthy of him in our lives:</hi> for want of a <hi>true and unfeigned purpoſe, deſire and endeavour, for our ſelves and all others under our power and charge, both in publike and private, in all duties we ow to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the example of a reall Reformation, that the Lord may turne away his wrath and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Churches and Kingdoms in truth and peace:</hi> Finally, for want of that <hi>Christian and brotherly charity and unity,</hi> that every where appears in many ſad rents and dangerous diviſions that daily in all places abound, threatning greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation then the ſword of the enemy, or any other judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is upon us.</p>
            <p>You ſee what a long roll, what a black catalogue may be brought in againſt us, how many ſins we have to ſpread
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113278:26"/> before the Lord this day, what great, what ſcarlet ſins we are guilty of, who yet are apt to <hi>put farre away the evil day,</hi> to grow confident that our danger is over, that we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee that adverſity which have come upon others in the Kingdome, and that God is now ſo faſt tied to us, as never to depart from us, nor to give over <hi>walking with us</hi> in all wayes of mercy and grace.</p>
            <p>This day is ſet apart for ſolemne, ſerious, publike humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and Sermons upon this day, are, or ſhould be ſo managed as to helpe us in this duty: to ſet our ſins before us with their ſeverall aggravations, that we might <hi>draw</hi> the more <hi>water</hi> of godly ſorrow out of our rocky hearts, <hi>and pour it out before the Lord,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> at <hi>Mizpeh</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.6.</note> O therefore, be afflicted, and mourn, and weep, rend your hearts, put your mouths in the duſt through ſhame and confuſion of face, and out of deſire to be humbled to the utmoſt, <hi>before the decree of Englands ruins bring forth</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, <hi>before the fierce anger of the Lord come upon you, before the day of the Lords anger come upon you</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Zeph. 2.2.</note>, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Take heed of turning theſe monethly humiliations into formalities, leſt we provoke God more by our hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall mock-faſts, then by any other our ſins, for which we pretend to be humbled on ſuch daies as theſe. Beware of that <hi>bull-ruſh</hi> humiliation which the Lord complains of, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.8. Who derides not that ridiculous folly of <hi>Lewes</hi> the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. who wore a <hi>Crucifix</hi> in his hat, in teſtimony of great devotion; and ſo often as he had ſworn an <hi>Oath,</hi> or committed other groſſe offence, he would take off his hat, and kiſſe his <hi>crucifix,</hi> thinking that a ſufficient ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for his fault, and then go ſin again as much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? But there is ſomewhat more to be done by thoſe that would indeed make their peace and <hi>agreement</hi> with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113278:26"/> God. <hi>Surely it is meet to be ſaid unto God, I have borne cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiſement, I will not offend any more: That which I ſee not, teach thou me; if I have done iniquity, I will do no more,</hi> Job 34.31, 32.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This leads me to the ſecond branch of the <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and which is the other main part of this dayes <hi>duty,</hi> namely, to labour, before we depart this place, to bring our hearts to come up to a full and perfect <hi>agreement with God.</hi> This is one of the great errands of all the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Chriſt, namely, to <hi>pray all</hi> to whom they come, <hi>in Chriſts ſtead, as though God did beſeech you by them, to be reconciled unto God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. Let the power of the death of Chriſt be applyed by faith, to eat out and kill that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall malice and enmity that naturally rageth in every one of our boſomes againſt God. <hi>Mortifie therefore your members which are upon the earth, fornication, uncleanneſſe, inordinate affection, evil concupiſcence, and covetouſneſſe which is Idolatry; for which things ſake the wrath of God comes upon the children of diſobedience,</hi> Col. 3.5, 6. Bring your hearts to a perfect compliance with God, in <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, reſolutions,</hi> and in all your <hi>actions;</hi> away with all ſelf-love and ſelf-ends. Men of private deſignes, will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the Kingdome, Religion, and all the world, if it were in their power, if temptations and opportunities be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, rather then be fruſtrate of their own ends; what ever ſhew of zeal for Chriſt and the Publike they pretend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in the carrying on of the Publike Cauſe. It was <hi>Calebs</hi> comfort, happineſſe and honour, that in managing the publike ſervice of <hi>Iſrael</hi> committed to him by <hi>Moſes, he followed God fully, Numb.</hi> 14.24. An excellent pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for you that are the heads and guides of our Tribes, who are now leading this poor ſinfull Nation thorow a ſharpe and tedious wilderneſſe, where we are to march
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113278:27"/> thorow rivers of blood, towards a firme and well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Peace and perfect Reformation. If any of you have private ends in this publike worke (which God forbid) we ſhall be bought and ſold (as ſometimes <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>her people</hi> were) not only <hi>for bond-men and bond-women,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſth. 7.4.</note> but <hi>to be deſtroyed, to be ſlain, and to periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be ſure of this, nothing but a firme <hi>agreement with God,</hi> and the <hi>power of godlineſse,</hi> can keep any of you all firme and conſtant to the Cauſe of God and his people. <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> was a man of as deep wiſedome, and as great a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to the intereſts and ſervice of <hi>David</hi> and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as is poſſible for any mortall to be towards any King or Kingdome in the world. Yet when <hi>Abſolom</hi> by wiles and promiſes of greater place and preferment, ſet upon him, he could not ſtand before ſuch temptations. Only an <hi>Huſhai,</hi> a faithfull, plain, publike-ſpirited man held it out, and at length had the happineſſe to overthrow the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of a farre deeper and ſubtle Counſellour then himſelfe, and thereby ſaved both a King and Kingdome. It is the honeſt, plain downright-hearted Counſellour (that ſcornes all private ends, out of ſupernaturall principles) that ſhall carry it at the long runne, and live to ſee all the <hi>Achitophels</hi> of the time ſent to hell in a ſtring, or in ſome other dreſſe.</p>
            <p>Renue Covenant with God this day, and do it heartily, it is a chief worke of the day. If <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> thought it neceſſary to enter into Covenant a ſecond time (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.16.) who had never violated their firſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; thinke it not ſuperfluous, but a matter of neceſſity, to renue that Covenant which we have every day broken, and that with a very high hand, by <hi>walking contrary unto him,</hi> for which <hi>he hath brought the ſword upon us, to avenge the quarrell of his Covenant</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Lev. 26.24, 25.</note>. But, do it in ſincerity: for, all haltings in a Covenant, are the greateſt provocations
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113278:27"/> that men obnoxious to wrath can poſſibly commit; that <hi>great ſinne against the Holy Ghoſt</hi> only excepted.</p>
            <p>Reſt not here, thinke it not enough to renue Covenant, but minde it and keep it. <hi>When thou vowest a vow unto God, deferre not to pay it: for he hath no pleaſure in fooles,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.4. Therefore God made a Law to binde men to perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance even of voluntary vows, to which they were no way tyed, but by their own voluntary choice. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.21, 22. <hi>When thou ſhalt vow a vow unto the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not ſlack to pay it: for the Lord thy God will ſurely require it of thee, and it would be ſinne unto thee.</hi> I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conſider all that you have Covenanted, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reformation.</hi> And herein let your ſelves be firſt firme and unmoveable, in ſuch Truths as all the people of God have unanimouſly imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as being undoubtedly founded on the word of God. Shift not opinions with the time; court no party, becauſe great and ſtrong; <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note>; nor deferre the doing thy duty for fear of a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. It is not in the worke of Chriſt, as in civil affairs: In civil buſineſſe of the ſtate, it is wiſedom to obſerve the genius of the people, and what they will bear: but in the things of Chriſt, it is duty to look only to what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, becauſe his Ordinances have this prerogative, <hi>to still the madneſſe of the people.</hi> Suſpect that man and his counſels, who caſteth off old principles received by all the Churches of Chriſt: and ſhun thoſe men that walke in the darke, that they may hold the fairer correſpondency with all ſects and opinions. A true godly man holds out his principles clearly to all the world (truth ſeeks no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: he that conceals his Tenets, lyes in the winde for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; and you are never ſure of him, nor know where to finde him, unleſſe you can diſcover his moſt hidden
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113278:28"/> ends and intereſts: And he that will not diſcover his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, will be ſure to hide his ends. There can be no great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evidence of a rotten heart, and baſe ends, then to be a weather-cock in matters of Religion. And commonly they are in the iſſues moſt pernicious to a ſtate, who, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of new light, can ſhift and change opinions, as men do faſhions: Liberty and licentiouſneſſe in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, is one of the greateſt in-lets to all corruptions in the ſtate: Be therefore zealous of promoting Reformation in a cleer and uniforme way, that all may know what to truſt unto. It is true, you muſt not run upon <hi>implicite faith:</hi> but then, take pains to be informed by thoſe whom you have called to adviſe withall: inquire into the full ſtrength of their Arguments held out by themſelves, and not reſt ſatisfied with ſuch abridgements and interpretations as their Adverſaries pleaſe to ſuggeſt. And if you will have the worke to proſper, ſet to it with one heart and one ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Be at peace among your ſelves, and with all thoſe that in ſincerity and plainneſſe of heart, deſire and endeavour to carry on the Lords worke with you, or under you. Stop your ears againſt all whiſperers, that ſeek to make or fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diviſions and quarrels, how ſpecious ſoever their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences be. If you be not <hi>agreed</hi> among your ſelves, how ſhall you <hi>walke together,</hi> in the cordiall, effectuall managing of any buſineſſe? yea, how is it poſſible for you to ſave the Kingdome from deſtruction? <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> being asked <hi>why</hi> Sparta <hi>had no walls?</hi> returned anſwer, that <hi>the Citizens agreed together.</hi> There is no fortification like to unity: whereas <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand.</hi> If you have any private differences, they are not to be now ſo much as remembred. <hi>Aristides</hi> and <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> the heads of two great Factions in <hi>Athens,</hi> when they ſaw the <hi>Perſian</hi> to take advantage of their diviſions, and to ſend an
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113278:28"/> Army to ſubdue them, met, and ſtruck hands, ſaying, <hi>here we lay down all our differences, untill we have put an end to the Perſian warre.</hi> Have Heathens done thus, and ſhall Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſtand upon Punctillo's of honour, when it is indeed a diſhonour to be ſo poor-ſpirited, and <hi>an honour to ceaſe from ſtrife?</hi> What got <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> and <hi>Hircanus</hi> by their implacable contending for ſoveraignty,<note place="margin">Joſeph. <hi>Antiq. lib.</hi> 14.</note> but only the opening of a way to <hi>Pompey</hi> to ſubdue both, and to put all the <hi>Jews</hi> under the <hi>Romane</hi> yoke? Was not <hi>diviſion</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when <hi>Titus</hi> came before it? And was not <hi>Constantinople</hi> loſt to <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great by the ſame means; whereas neither <hi>Amurath</hi> his father, nor <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jazet</hi> his grandfather, got any thing but loſſe of men and honour, in attempting that City in former times, when it was better at unity within it ſelfe? It was the wiſedom of <hi>Alcibiades</hi> and <hi>Nicias,</hi> two great men of <hi>Athens,</hi> that were at variance, when they ſaw the wickedneſſe of <hi>Hyperbolus</hi> in ſeeking the baniſhment of one of them two (he cared not which) by the Law of <hi>Oſtraciſme</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">This Law began about that time, by which ſuch as grew too ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant in wealth or power, were baniſhed the City for ten years, that they might not be the heads of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which might preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Plut.</hi> in <hi>Nicias.</hi>
               </note>, that he might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards more eaſily deſtroy the other: they ſecretly met, compoſed their differences, and joyned both their parties together, and by that device procured his baniſhment which had ſought theirs. Do but ſerve ſome of thoſe ſo, that labour to ſet you at odds, and it would be a great means of much quiet and ſafety both to you and us.</p>
            <p>I conclude all with that of the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.15, 16. <hi>Hear ye and give ear, be not proud: for the Lord hath ſpoken. Give glory to the Lord your God, before he cauſe darkneſſe, and before you stumble upon the darke mountains, and while ye look for light, he turne it into the ſhadow of death, and make it groſſe darkneſſe</hi> over this Kingdome forever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Errata,</hi> Pag. 1. mar. l 1. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 11. l. 13. dele <hi>ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
